A Guide to a Commonplace Book of Early American Poems
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6329
Commonplace Book of Early American Poems 1777-1788
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6329
1 bound volume
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, April 16, 1960.
Scope and Content
The compiler of this 382-page manuscript volume was Hugh McConnel of Fisk Kill Landing, New Jersey. (See "author's inscription" on page 34, etc. The compiler docketed several of the entries "Fish Kill," "Landing," or alternatively, "Fish Kill Barricks," "Barricks," "Barr-s," or "B.") The volume was evidently compiled 1777-1788, but includes items originating at earlier dates. Few of the entries are attributed to other authors. While some of the unattributed entries (such as the anecdotes) may simply have been recorded by the compiler, it appears that a majority of the entires may be Hugh McConnel's original composition.
The volume contains approximately four hundred entries: American, English, and Masonic poems, songs, and verse, as well as anecdotes, maxims, essays, and historical notes. Major themes include American patriotism, anti-British sentiment, wit and humor, military history, love, philosophy, ethics, and Freemasonry. A number of the songs and anecdotes are somewhat risque. A watercolored fraktur appears on page 61, and an engraving, "New York Packet," appears on page 187.
Pages 184-186, 299, 338, and 351 are blank.
Items listed in order of their appearance.
Condition
It appears that at least one page at the beginning of the volume was lost, and significant portions of pages 59-62, 97-98, 101-102, 313-314, and 341-346 were cut or torn out prior to the acquisition of the volume; other textual loss has resulted from damage to the edges of the pages and the acidity of the ink used. Due to its deteriorated condition, the volume was debound, and the pages deacidifed and laminated by the Barrow process.
Item listing
- Verse: "... all for America ....", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "A Song", n.d.; AMs
  [The bird that hears her nestlings cry...]
- Phyllis Wheatley to "His Excellency Genl. Washington" (encloses following poem), 1775 Oct 26; AL
- Poem by Phyllis Wheatley: "Celestial choir enthron'd in realms of light...", [1775 Oct]; AMs
- Poem: "A Rebus", n.d.; AMs
  [What's fickle as the wind, the French delight...]
- Quotations from Benjamin Franklin: "Begin this year with serious thoughts...", 1778 Jul 8; AMs
- Poem: "A Rebus Upon the Name of a City...", n.d.; AMs
  [To the Brethren most ancient, [may] I them address...]
- Poem: "The Rebus", n.d.; AMs
  [Take that cardinal virtue most blended with art...]
- Poem: "A Thought", n.d.; AMs
  [How like the fleeting wind, away...]
- Poem: "A Song on the Times", n.d.; AMs
  [My muse now thy aid and assistance we claim...]
- Verse: "... written upon a pane of glass at Moffat ...", n.d.; AMs
  [From Scottish mountains hid in snow...]
- Poem: "The Tale of the Monk and Jew (Versified)", AMs
  [An unbelieving Jew one day was skating o'er...]
- Historical note re: New York, 1778 Feb 12; AMs
- Poem: "Answer to a Rebus Oblong", 1778 Feb 12; AMs
  [Is prudence the cardinal virtue you mean...]
- Poem: "Original Epigram to Miss [Polly]", n.d.; AMs
  [Could I command the riches of a crown...]
- Poem: "A Song", n.d.; AMs
  [Hark, hark, the joy-inspiring horn...]
- Historical note re: General Burgoyne, 1777 Oct 17; AMs
- Poem: "Corydon and Phyllis, A Song", AMs
  [Her sheep had in clusters [crept] close to a grove...]
- Maxim re: lawyers, n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Fair Hebe, A Song", n.d.; AMs
  [Fair Hebe I left with a cautious [design]...]
- Anecdote: "The Tale of the Taylor and Apothecary", AMs
- Verse [by Alexander Pope]: "Lo, the poor Indian...", AMs
- Poem: "A Song for America", n.d.; AMs
  [The world is like a whirly gig and swiftly spins...]
- Maxim re: spinners, 1778; AMs
- Poem: "A New Song", n.d.; AMs
  [Hark, hark, the joyful news is come...]
- Verse: "Observe the bee...", n.d.; AMs
- Dialogue: "The Politicians", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "A Song of Plato's", 1778 Feb 17; AMs
  [Says Plato why should man be vain...]
- Play: "Mrs. Scrapely Robbed", n.d.; AMs
- Soliloquy: "Epicurus to Idomeneus", n.d.; AMs
- Verse: "The lark's shrill note...", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Horrors of Wars with America", n.d.; AMs
  [Now has the Brittens snatch'd a short repast...]
- Excerpt from "Two [sic] Merry Wives of Windsor" [by William Shakespeare], AMs
- Poem: "An Ode from the 19th Psalm", n.d.; AMs
  [The lofty pillars of the sky...]
- Maxim re: laws, n.d.; AMs
- Essay: "Remonstrance, and Contempt of Pride", AMs
- Poem: "To the [Mighty] T. W.", n.d.; AMs
  [Peace worthy shade! Peace to thy virtuous soul...]
- Verse: "New lawyers in the City Hall...", n.d.; AMs
- Maxim re: liberty/ with author's inscription, 1779 Feb 4; AMs
- Poem: "To Miss J[enny] W.", n.d.; AMs
  [When late, oppress'd with heart-felt grief...]
- Poem: "A Riddle", n.d.; AMs
  [Before that noble creature man, sprang from the dust...]
- Notes (possibly answers to previous item?), n.d.; AMs
- Poems (3): "Epitaphs", n.d.; AMs
- author's inscription, 1780 Nov 27; signature
- (Belongings of) "The First Commissioner Going Out to America...", 1778 Mar 13; AMs
- Poem: "Upon the Largest Jewel's Dropping Out of his Majesty's Crown on his Coronation", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Upon Marriage", n.d.; AMs
  [Man whilst alone in Eden mourn'd his state...]
- Poem: "How to Choose a Wife as the Poet Saith", n.d.; AMs
  [In choice of a wife, prefer the modest, chaste...]
- Poem: "To the Offended Fair Sex", AMs
  [When Sheba's beautious queen urg'd on fame...]
- Essay: "On Winter Blasts", 1777 Dec 1; AMs
- Essay: "Contentment and Covetousness, Temperance and Gluttony, Sobriety and Drunkeness Compared", AMs
- Verse: "If you desire health to be lasting..." (with author's inscription, partly in code), n.d.; AMs
- "The Providential Escape of the Protestants in Ireland from Queen Mary's Persecution in 1558", 1779 Feb 16; AMs
- Quotes (29): "Toasts", 1779 Mar 8; AMs
- Poem: "The Drum" [The drum's abetting now my boys...], 1779 Mar 12; AMs
- Poem: "Hail Americans Hail", n.d.; AMs
  [Hail Americans hail, still unrivaled in fame...]
- Note re: snowstorm, 1779 Mar 15; AMs
- "To General Howe" from "A Tar", 1777 May 26; AL
- Verse:"Past, present, future in His sight...", n.d.; AMs
- Essay: "The Repentance & Confession of a Tory", 1779 Mar 26; AMs
- Quote: "Anecdote of General Moultrie", n.d.; AMs
- Anecdote re: a baker, n.d.; AMs
- Anecdote re: a fat gentleman, n.d.; AMs
- Anecdote re: goats, n.d.; AMs
- author's inscription, 1781 Jan 4; signature
- Biblical parody: "The Acts of the Americans...", 1779 Oct 17; AMs
- Poem: "On the Soldier", n.d.; AMs
  [Eager the soldier meets his desperate foe... (with watercolor fraktur)]
- Essay: "Amongst all the diversions of the Indians, that of their masks...", AMs
- Verse [by "S.D."]: "When Phaeton, that simple sot...", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "A New Song", 1779 Nov 25; AMs
  [Come all you Americans that's faithful and brave...]
- Verse: "When rugged winter pours her stores...", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "A Song", 1779 Dec 9; AMs
  [And are you sure the news is true...]
- Note re: protecting cabbages, n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Kat Take My Tobacco Box", 1779 Dec 23; AMs
  [Th'o the fate of battle on to morrow wait...]
- Poem: "A New Song on Liberty", 1779 Dec 29; AMs
- "Vain Briton [boast] no longer...", 1780 Jan 30; AMs
- Maxims (5) re: behavior, n.d.; AMs
- Satire [by Thomas Waring]: "The Last Will and Testament of England", 1779 Apr 19; AMs
- Poem: "War", n.d.; AMs
  ["War; how I hate thy horrid name..."]
- Verse: "Love is the monarch passion...", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "King George the 3rd, Soliloquy", 1779 May 22; AMs
  [O [damn] this congress, [damn] each upstart state...]
- Verse:"Lord, save us for thy glorious name...", 1780 Feb 20; AMs
- Parody: "Sir Henry Clinton's Soliloquy...", 1779; AMs
- Verse: "Force never yet a gen'rous breast..." (with author's inscription), 1780 Feb 21; AMs
- Poem: "A New Song Called the Young Irishman's Tail", n.d.; AMs
  [As I was a-walking one morning...]
- Maxim re: wit, n.d.; AMs
- Satire: "The Celebrated Dutch and German Dialogue Between Mynheer Eupharson...", 1780 Mar 16; AMs
- Note re: snowstorm, 1780 Mar 17; AMs
- Poem: "General Wolfe, A New Song", 1780 May 22; AMs
  [In a mouldering cave, where the wretched retreat...]
- Note re: mythology, n.d; AMs
- Poem: "Upon a Widow's Wooden Tomb-Stone", 1780 May 23; AMs
  [Grieve not for me my dearest dear...]
- Verse: "Sweet Nymphis, accept the magic bread...", 1780 May 23; AMs
- 18 ribald anecdotes, 1780 May 24-1780 Jun 3; AMs
- Poem: "Liberty Tree - A New Song", n.d.; AMs
  [In a chariot of light from the region of day...]
- 12 ribald anecdotes, n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Adam's Sleep", 1780 Jul 12; AMs
  [Sleep, Adam, sleep, and take thy rest...]
- Poem: "Cure for G--n Si--s", n.d.; AMs
  [As fair Olinda sat beneath a shady tree...]
- Poem [by John Dayden]: "A Song", AMs
  [Silvia the fair, in the bloom of fifteen...]
- Poem: "A Song - Mason's Daughter", n.d.; AMs
  [A mason's daughter, fair and young...]
- Poem: "Song, Once I was Blind", AMs
  [Once I was blind and could not see...]
- Verse: "Oh, fly, my queen, from this devouring..." (with author's inscription), 1781 Jan 1; AMs
- Poem: "A Song - King Solomon", n.d.; AMs
  [King Solomon, that wise projector...]
- Poem: "A Song, A Health", n.d.; AMs
  [A health to our sisters let's drink...]
- Poem: "Ye Thrice Happy Few, A Song" (a Masonic song), n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "We Have No Idle Prating - A Song" (a Masonic song), n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "A Mason One Time, A Song", n.d.; AMs
  [A mason one time was cast for a crime...]
- Poem: "Come Let Us Prepare, A Song" (a Masonic song), n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "To All Who Masonry Despise, A Song", n.d.; AMs
  [To all who..., this counsel I bestow...]
- Poem: "Song - The French Fleet is at Last Come", n.d.; AMs
  [Freedom is a real treasure...]
- Poem: "Assembl'd and Tyl'd, A Song" (a Masonic song), AMs
- Poem: "Come Follow, Follow Me, A Song" (a Masonic song), n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Ye People Who Laugh" (a Masonic song), n.d.; AMs
- Soliloquy: "Jacob Halsey's Speech", 1780 Dec 20; AMs
- Poem: "Epitaph", 1781 Jan 3; AMs
  [Here lies DuVall, Reader if male thou art...]
- Note re: forces commanded by Count De Barras, Monsieur De Monteil, Monsieur Bougainville, and Monsieur le Compt De Grasse, AMs
- Poem: "The Irish Gariel, A Song", 1781 Jan 15; AMs
  [On day as I was walking down a river side...]
- Poem: "A New Song", 1781 Jan 19; AMs
  [Come on my harts of tempred steel...]
- Poem: "A New Song", 1781 Jan 20; AMs
  [God save America, free from tyrannic sway...]
- Poem: "A Song", 1781; AMs
  [A [crab louse] I am, from a [crab louse] I came...]
- Anecdotes (3): "Political Fables by the Celebrated D.F.", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "To the Y, Y, & H, Y,", n.d.; AMs
  [What thanks, my friend should be given...]
- Note re: snowstorm, 1781 Jan 23; AMs
- Poem: "Life is Short and Miserable", AMs
  [Ah! Few and full of sorrow are the days...]
- author's inscription, 1781 Jan 24; signature
- Maxims: "One Hundred and Twenty-six Good Rule's Laid Down for Youth", 1781 Jan 26; AMs
- Maxims: "More Good Rules for Youth, in Alphabetical Order", n.d.; AMs
- Maxims "Twenty-four Excellent Verses for Young Men or Old, ...", 1781; AMs
- Poem: "On the Flight of Benedict Arnold", n.d.; AMs
  [Fame did he seek, he surely has it...]
- Parable [by Raif Huxley]: "The Boy and the Horse, or an Appendix to the King of England's Speech...July 8, 1780", 1781 Jan 29; AMs
- Anecdote: "On the Villain, Arnold's, Arrival...", 1781; AMs
- Poem: "From Lucr--s by Mr --", 1781 Feb 2; AMs
  [Then like a sailor by the tempest hurl'd...]
- Poem: "A Few Verses Sent By a Friend to One Who Twice Ventur'd... in Marriage", AMs
  [The husband's the pilot, the wife is the ocean...]
- Verse: "Cupid, the slyest rogue alive...", 1781 Feb 13; AMs
- Poem: "An Elegy", 1781 Feb 27; AMs
  [The scene of death is clos'd, the mournful strain...]
- Poem: "The Batchelor's Wish", n.d.; AMs
  [If marriage gives happiness to life...]
- Note re: Washington's commission, 1775 Jun 15; AMs
- 27 anecdotes, n.d.; AMs
- Note re: rainstorm, 1781 Mar 2; AMs
- Note re: snowstorm, 1781 Mar 7; AMs
- author's inscription, 1781 Mar 10; signature
- author's inscription, n.d.; signature
- Poem: "A Song", 1781 Mar 21; AMs
  [Fairwell to you sweet Ireland...]
- Poem: "A New, Old Song, That's Good Dutch", n.d.; AMs
  [Bumpers about my friendly circle...]
- Satire: "A [Recipe] to Make a True, Blue [Patriot] in Three Days", n.d.; AMs
- Anecdote re: King George, n.d.; AMs
- Soliloquy: "The Last Speech of William Fr--n, Esq. Who Was Executed in New York", 1776 Mar 18; AMs
- Note re: phase of the moon], 1781 Apr 23; AMs
- Anecdotes (10) re: King George, n.d.; AMs
- author's inscription, 1781 Apr 28; signature
- Poem: "The Humble Petition of Want and Misery, Addressed to All Christian...", 1781 May 7; AMs
  [While thro' the drear of frost and snow...]
- Verse: "To public bodies and to all that colonies we late did call...", AMs
  [parody on Aristophanes]
- Poem: "A Song", 1781 Nov 6; AMs
  [He comes, he comes, the hero comes...]
- Poem: "A Rebus; Fresh from a Votary of Phebus", 1781 Sep 24; AMs
  [The place I admire, and whose people I love...]
- Poem: "A Rebus", 1781 Oct 22; AMs
  [The half of a part of an egg fulle of meat...]
- Poem: "An Epistle from Lord Cornwallis to Sir Henry Clinton", n.d.; AMs
  [From clouds of smoke and flames that round me glow...]
- author's inscription, 1781 Nov 8; signature
- Poem: "On the Day That Genl. Burgoyne Fell", 1781 Nov 9; AMs
  [While scenes of transport, every breast inspire...]
- Poem: "A Epigram, By a Nova Scotia Refugee....", n.d.; AMs
  [Bravely to aim at something, to make known...]
- Poem: "A Contrast Between Sir William Howe And Sir Henry Clinton, Dedicated to Lord North", AMs
  [England, I feel for what I'm sure you must...]
- Poem: "Thoughts on Sleep", 1781 Nov 13; AMs
  [Since sleep, death's image (nightly warnings...)]
- Poem: "A New Song", n.d.; AMs
  "July they say, the fifteenth day..."
- Note re: sickness, 1783 Jun 19-1783 Sep 2; AMs
- "New York Packet" on engraved leaf with inscriptions: "James McConnel, nailer, near Winsor"; "John McConnel, taylor, Albany"; "Hugh McConnel - brothers"; "William McConnel, Ireland", 1783 Oct 2; AMs
- "From the New York Gazette..." s/ James Rivington, 1781 Nov 1, 1781 Nov 23; AMs
  [re: auction of possessions of Sir Henry Clinton]
- Poem: "From the [Pennsylvania Gazette]", 1781 Nov 26; AMs
  [Hark! Hear the trumpet's pleasing sound...]
- Poem: "A Fable - Addressed to the Modern Duellists", 1781 Nov 30; AMs
  ['Twas on a time (I shan't say when)...]
- Poem: "A Song. Hail Masonry Divine!", n.d.; AMs
  [Hail Masonry, thou craft divine...]
- Poem: "Song, Come, Come, My Brethren Dear" (a Masonic song), 1781Dec 1; AMs
- Poem: "Song. When Earth's Foundation First Was Laid" (a Masonic song), AMs
- author's inscription, 1781 Dec 1; signature
- Poem: "Song, Genius of Masonry Descend" (a Masonic song), 1781 Dec 3; AMs
- Poem: "Song, On, On, My Dear Brethren, etc." (a Masonic song), n.d.; AMs
- author's inscription, n.d.; signature
- Satire: "Wanted. For the Next Campaign in North-America", 1781 Nov 20; AMs
  [A Commander in Chief for the British armies...]
- Poem [by "M."]: "Epigram Occasioned by the Title of Rivington's Royal Gazette Being Scarcely Legible", n.d.; AMs
  [Says Satan to Jammy, I hold you a bet...]
- Poem: "From a Late Irish Paper. Paddy's Address to John Bull...", n.d.; AMs
  [By your leave, gossip John, by my faith, 'tis so long...]
- Anecdote: "A Ball", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "An Epilogue", 1782 Mar 7; AMs
  [Well heavens be prais'd, the mighty secret's out...]
- "General Return of Officers and Privates Surrendered Prisoners...", 1781 Oct 19; AMs
- Note re: rainstorm, 1782 Mar 8; AMs
- 5 anecdotes, 1782 Mar 9 -11; AMs
- Satire: "Political Sales By Auction...", n.d.; AMs
  [The British rights in America, consisting...]
- Satire: "Also By James Twitcher and Co.", AMs
  [The remaining stock in trade of the Royal Navy...]
- Verse: "Hail, auspicious morning, clear...", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "On Valentine's Day", n.d.; AMs
  [Now nature's genial instinct fires...]
- Anecdote: "An Anecdote" [re: Lord Cornwallis], 1782 Mar 12; AMs
- Poem: "A Speech That Should Have Been Spoken by the King...of Britain...", n.d.; AMs
  [My Lords, I can hardly from weeping refrain...]
- Maxims (3): "Select Sentences", n.d.; AMs
- Essay: "Strictures on Fear, Cowardice, And Valour", AMs
- Verse: "The trumpets terribly from afar...", 1782 Mar 14; AMs
- author's inscription), 1782 Mar 14; signature
- Homily: "To the Reader", 1782 Mar 24; AMs
- Maxims (5): "Select Sentences", 1783 Dec 1; AMs
- Anecdote: "Anecdote of David Hume", 1782 Mar 26; AMs
- Poem: "A New Song. Tune of Jolly Mortals", 1783 Nov 10; AMs
  [Manly Yorkers, fill your glasses...]
- author's inscription, 1783 Nov 10; signature
- Poem: "A Song - Cato's Advice", 1783 Nov 10; AMs
  [Says Cato, why should men repine...]
- Essay: "Expensiveness in Apparel", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "A Speech on the War", 1783 Nov 11; AMs
  [Grown sick of war, and war's alarms...]
- Poem: "The Wish", 1783 Nov 12; AMs
  [I've often wish'd to be the god of love...]
- Poem: "An Epitaph on Human Life", 1783 Nov 12; AMs
  [Be early wise, lest prudence come too late...]
- Satire: "Translation of a Political Squib Handed About at Paris - The Fourteen Alls", AMs
- Poem: "On Friendship", 1783 Nov 12; AMs
  [Tell me ye knowing and discerning few...]
- Poem: "The Choice of a Young Lady", 1783 Nov 13; AMs
  [If marriage ever be my lot in life...]
- Poem: "The Lady's Choice - An Ode", 1783; AMs
  [Grant me kind heaven! The man that's brave...]
- "A List of the Negroes Committed on Account of the Conspiracy in New York ... in 1741", n.d.; AMs
- "A List of the White Persons Committed on Account of the Conspiracy in New York ... in 1741", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Epigram on Old N--k", 1783 Nov 14; AMs
  [Says Nan, one day, to her husband Dick...]
- Poem: "The Lion, the Mastives, and Other Beasts. - A Fable", AMs
  [In former days -no matter when -four-footed beasts resembled men...]
- Anecdote re: place-names, 1783 Nov 29; AMs
- 3 maxims, n.d.; AMs
- Anecdote re: Secretary Fox, n.d.; AMs
- "To Benedict Arnold", 1783 Nov 20; AMs
- Poem: "Marriage - A Le Mode", n.d.; AMs
  [Marriage, that makes two bodies one...]
- Poem: "A Song", n.d.; AMs
  [Columbia, Columbia, to glory arise...]
- Note: "O, Sweet Ireland, I Smell You Now", AMs
- Anecdote: "The Old Man and His Ass", 1783 Nov 21; AMs
- Anecdote: "The Contented Porter", 1783; AMs
- Story: "Example of Veracity", 1783 Nov 22; AMs
- Story: "Labour", 1783 Nov 22; AMs
- Maxim: "Of Industry and Frugality", 1783 Nov 22; AMs
- Maxim: "A Caution in Dealing", 1783 Nov 25; AMs
- Map re: fortifications at junction of Mystic River and Charles River, AMs
- Play by the Rev. Mr. Ogden: "The Libertine Reclaimed: A Dialogue", 1783 Dec 3; AMs
- Poem: "The Present Age", 1783 Dec 5; AMs
  [No more my friends, of vain applause...]
- Anecdote: "An Anecdote", 1783 Dec 6; AMs
- Poem: "The Meaning of Mr. C. Fox's Speech, Versified Hubridrastically", 1783; AMs
- "Extract of a Letter from Capt. Courish, of the New England Militia, Dated: Albany, March 7, 1782", AL
  [encloses letter from James Craufurd detailing booty of scalps and Indian petitions]
- Satire: "A Dialogue Between Prince William Henry and Henry Clinton, at their Second Interview in New York", AMs
- Poem: "A Pasquinade", 1783 Dec 8; AMs
  [You know there goes a tale...]
- Poem: "A New Song", 1783 Dec 10; AMs
  [Fame let thy trumpet sound...]
- Poem: "A New Song, on the Celebration of the Birth of the Dauphin", n.d.; AMs
  [Ye sons of Mars attend...]
- Poem: "On Pride", 1783; AMs
  [Pride, the consumptive child of a weak mind...]
- Poem: "Rivington's Reflections", n.d.; AMs
  [The more I reflect, the more plain it appears...]
- Poem: "To J. D., Esq.", 1783 Dec 11; AMs
  [To blast thy fame though pining envy tries...]
- Poem: "A New Song", n.d.; AMs
  [In a chariot of light from the regions above...]
- Essay: "The Sum of Human Liberty", n.d.; AMs
- Poem: "Represent the Mind of Man", 1783; AMs
  [A watch may represent the mind of man...]
- Essay: "The Character of an Atheist", 1783; AMs
- Essay: "Encomium on Patriotism", 1783; AMs
- Poem: "Versification of the British King's Late Speech Before...Parliament", 1783 Dec 12; AMs
  [The unweary'd progress which you've made...]
- Poem: "The N. Y. P.", 1783 Dec 14; AMs
  [Grave autumn clad in hazy-tintur'd hue...]
- Poem: "An Address to the Ladies, by their Best Friend, Sincerity", 1783 Dec 16; AMs
  [A time there was of manners plain...]
- Essay: "Matrimony", 1783 Dec 16; AMs
- Poem: "Rivington's Last Will and Testament", AMs
  [Since life is uncertain, and no one can say...]
- Poem: "Epigram", 1783 Dec 17; AMs
  [Britannia's dead, her glory now is o'er...]
- Essay: "On Self-Interest", 1783; AMs
- Essay: "An Essay on Avarice", [1783 Dec] 18; AMs
- Essay: "On Death", 1783 Dec 18; AMs
- Poem: "The Picture of Old Age, Paraphrased from...12th Chapter of Ecclestiastes", n.d.; AMs
  [My son, attentive hear the voice of [truth]...]
- Poem: "The Following is a Versification of the King's Speech to...Parliament", 1783 Dec 20; AMs
  [This twenty-seventh of November...]
- Poem: "To the Memory of General Lee...", n.d.; AMs
  [Warrior, farewell! Eccentrically brave...]
- Satire: "A Curious Anecdote", 1783 Dec 22; AMs
  [re: why Nova Scotia exists]
- Poem: "O the Tories in New York. A Song...", n.d.; AMs
  [Of all the dirty Tory race...]
- Obituary: "To All Christian Whigs", n.d.; AMs
  [re: Levi Pawling, d. 1782 Apr 30]
- author's inscription, 1783 Dec 29; signature
- Essay: "To the Man of Pleasure", 1783 Dec 30; AMs
- Essay: "Why is a Gardener the Most Extraordinary Man in the World?", n.d.; AMs
- Verse: "Seventeen hundred and eighty-three is now forever past..." (with author's inscription), 1783 Dec 31; AMs
- Poem: "An Ode for the New Year", 1784 Jan 1; AMs
  [Let the voice of music breathe...]
- Poem: "The Disappointed Lover", 1784 Jan 1; AMs
  [Fair Celia of yon yellow hill...]
- Poem: "An Epigram", 1784; AMs
  [Great bodies move slow I've heard said...]
- Poem: "The Humble Petition of Honest Hugh Gaine", n.d.; AMs
  [To the Senate of York, with all due submission...]
- Note re: snowstorm, 1784 Jan 6; AMs
- Maxim re: common sense, 1784 Jan 10; AMs
- Anecdote: "A Curious and Jocose Paragraph", AMs
- Anecdote: "Anecdote of Louis XII", 1784 Jan 13; AMs
- Anecdote: "The Following Anecdote May Be Depended on as a Fact", 1784 Jan 14; AMs
  [re: the accidental destruction of the King of Portugal's china by Burgoyne's wife]
- Anecdote re: Sir Charles Wager, 1784 Jan 16; AMs
- Poem: "Avarice", n.d.; AMs
  [Can av'rice give content: the miser view...]
- Poem: "To the Green Wood Gang Wi Me", n.d.; AMs
  [To speer my love wi glances fair...]
- "A Droll Epitaph...", n.d.; AMs
  [re: John Webb, d. 1746 May 3]
- Maxim re: words, n.d.; AMs
- Essay: "Dissolution of Manners", 1784; AMs
- Essay: "Conscious Freedom the Truest Dignity", [1784] Jan 19; AMs
- Essay: "An Essay on Hope", 1784 Jan 19; AMs
- Essay: "On Flattery", 1784 Jan 20; AMs
- Poem: "The Tory's Soliloquy", 1784; AMs
  [It must be so -farewell my native land...]
- Anecdote re: peace, 1784 Jan 23; AMs
- "Copy of a Letter from Kouinsburgh, Poland", AMs
  [re: birth of quintuplets]
- Satire: "An Extempore Sermon Preached by a Lover of Me", 1784 Jan 24; AMs
- Essay: "The language of the heart...", n.d.; AMs
- Story: "A Turkish Tale", 1784 Feb 5; AMs
- Essay: "In Praise of Virtue", 1784; AMs
- Essay: "Character of a True Friend", AMs
- Anecdote: "A Humorous Tale", 1784; AMs
- Poem: "A Poem", 1784 Mar 19; AMs